Guide to the Joshua Rashaad McFadden photographs, 2015-2016 RL.11527
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joshua Rashaad McFadden photographs
2015-2016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
McFadden, Joshua
RL.11527
0.5 Linear Feet 1 box 20 prints
Collection consists of 20 13x19 inch color inkjet photographic collages featuring portraits of young African American men, taken by McFadden, paired with reproduction color portraits of their fathers when they were younger, and a handwritten personal narrative by each youth about what it means to be an African American man in the 21st century. There is also a print with McFadden and his father. Many of the fathers appear in military uniforms. Topics expressed in the personal narratives include stereotypes as well as new definitions of black masculinity; the construction of and attitudes towards race, gender, and sexuality; generational issues; and relationships with fathers. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
20 color photographic prints
Biographical / Historical
Joshua Rashaad McFadden, artist and author, is originally from Rochester, New York. During his undergraduate years at Elizabeth City State University in North Carolina, he began to make photographs as a fine art practice. McFadden attended Savannah College of Art and Design where he obtained his Master of Fine Art.
In response to recent incidents of police brutality and the murders of African American men and women, McFadden created the photographic series "After Selma." Since its release in April 2015, McFadden was named one of the top emerging talents in the world by LensCulture and received the first place International Photography Award (IPA, 2015) for "After Selma." He won the first place IPA award again in 2016 for his series and book Come to Selfhood.
McFadden has since been published in EyesOpen Magazine, Slate Magazine, and the New York Times. In 2017 McFadden was recognized by Time Magazine as one of "12 African American Photographers You Should Follow Right Now."
McFadden is the winner of the 2017 Duke University Archive of Documentary Arts Award for Documentarians of Color.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Joshua Rashaad McFadden photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2017.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The photographs in this collection were printed on Exhibition Fiber Epson photography paper using a Epson SureColor P9000 Commercial Edition Printer.
Scope and Contents
Collection consists of 20 13x19 inch color inkjet photographic collages featuring portraits of young African American men, taken by McFadden, paired with reproduction color portraits of their fathers when they were younger, and handwritten personal narratives, one to three paragraphs long, by each youth about what it means to be an African American man in the 21st century. One print is of McFadden and his father, and includes a reproduction of his father's Selective Service card.
Topics expressed in the personal narratives include stereotypes as well as new definitions of black masculinity; the construction of and attitudes of others as well as themselves towards race, gender, and sexuality; generational issues; and relationships with fathers. Many of the fathers served in the Armed Forces, and appear in their portraits in military uniforms.
From the artist's statement: "How does one begin to challenge the misguided perceptions that decrease the quality of living for young African American men? Furthermore, how does the African American man position himself in a society that does not acknowledge his true identity? African American men and stories of their intersecting identities unrecognized in forums that allow these positive images to become a part of the dominant narrative of African American men. As a photographic artist, I chose to use contemporary portraiture, the vernacular image, qualitative data, and positioning to expose this narrative with Come to Selfhood."
"Come to Selfhood explores African American male identity, masculinity, notions about the father figure, and the photographic archive by providing a frame of reference that visually articulates the diverse identities of young Black men. By delving into ideas of history, role models, and varied experiences, Come to Selfhood makes the previously invisible Black man, accurately and meaningfully visible."
For this body of work, McFadden received the 2017 Duke University Archive of Documentary Arts Award for Documentarians of Color.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
African American men -- Family relationships; African American men -- Portraits; African American men -- Psychology; African American men -- Social conditions; African American men -- Social life and customs; African American youth -- Attitudes; African American youth -- Personal narratives; African American youth -- Portraits; Masculinity -- United States; Racism -- United States; United States -- Race relations; United States -- Social conditions -- 21st century; Color photographs; Digital prints; Inkjet prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Come to Selfhood, 2015-2016
  Scope and Contents
  Series of 20 13x19 inch color inkjet prints by Joshua McFadden, organized in original order as received by print number.
  - Jamel Jones left, and his father, James Jones, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0001)
    Wow. It'd probably be a combination of people and traits I find impressive. My dad's super diligent, loving and one of the most intelligent people I know. My uncle Pete's always involved in the community as a leader. And my granddad Albert loved life and lived it to the fullest. He had this uncanny sharp memory, able to pick up a conversation at the exact point you left it. It's surprising when he had seven kids and loads of grandchildren that he could give them all individual attention. I do have to thank my family for giving me a clearer picture of being a man.
    I identify as a black male. I don't see being black as a negative thing. For me, I get to be a part of a rich legacy of struggle and triumph. I'm a part of one of the most creative groups of people on the planet and a real leader of change. I'm good with that. I'm not going to let others color the way I view myself, my family and my history.
    We're extraordinary individuals regardless (and in spite of) oppression. Granted, if we weren't dealing with oppression, we could accomplish a lot more in a shorter amount of time. We're a monolithic group, but I find more of us tend to lead in our respective fields (art, science, psychology, etc.) with great results.
  - Brittonius Lyle left, and his grandfather, Thomas E. Lyle, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0002)
    As a black nerd, super heroes were my ideal figures that represent black male masculinity. Given there were and still so few it really made it easier for me to choose, specifically, John Stewart as the Green Lantern, Virgil Hawkins as static. Both these men possess excellent qualities for young black males to look up to strong, bold, brave, resourceful, level-headed, talented and role models for their community. The fact that Static looked up to Green Lantern as a role model for black super heroes was inspiring. These characters helped shape me as a young black male today.
  - Johnathan Marshall left, and his father, John Marshall, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0003)
    Human. Plain and simple. We cry, laugh, fight, create, love, sympathize, dream, just live like the rest of the human race.
    My granddad is that figure of masculinity for me. I watched him work day to day, provide for our household and coach my uncles and cousins into adulthood. He was reserved, funny and confident in his masculinity.
    Positive self-talk, as well as setting goals, have always helped me ignore the bullshit America has to offer black men. Finding my place outside of having to rely on the dominant culture and relying on myself cements my positive identity.
  - Brian Lawrey left, and his father, James Lawrey, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0004)
    Masculinity as a black man is remaining genuine. Believing in your movements by moving with a strong moral purity. Having an innocence at the core of wisdom leading the male along his path and resonating his joy through action. A black male in America is tougher. I personally do not like America due to it sticking a target on my back. "America" is an adjunct of where I reside currently. I have learned the "idea" of freedom in its constitution, yet I rely on my own strength and history to create my freedom. America is a house to me as a black male, not my home.
  - Cameron Goins left, and his father, Keith Goins, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0005)
    We're violent, we're ignorant, we're criminals, we're loud, we're aggressive, we sell drugs, we trap. These perceptions impact me every day because as a black male I am automatically stereotyped because of my skin as opposed to my character. I am constantly judged due to the medias perception. They have given me insight to how to bounce back and how to grow from experiences and turn the negatives into life lessons.
  - Christian Cody left, and his father, Ywahnos Cody, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0006)
    Andre 3000 came to mind first, so I'll use him as an example. I admire how he exists within the Hip-hop world without selling himself to be the stereotypical rap icon. He has a strong sense of self-expression undiluted by his surroundings. I like when men aren't afraid to show themselves. To me black masculinity is a liquid; loose and easily manipulated. It can take many forms. I'd say that my own identity as a black male would be characterized by intelligent, hardworking, and loving. That is who I am and what I have experienced.
  - David Chapman left, and his father, Earl Chapman, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0007)
    No, because I identify myself as a black man. The subtle yet distinct change in terminology from "male" to "men" makes all the difference between my physical and spiritual being.
  - David Williams left, and his father, David Williams, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0008)
    There is no Doubting my ethnicity. My skin is a smooth cocoa brown, my nose is round and wide, my hair is curly and I am blessed with talents with only a black man can have, and it brings me a greater sense of pride. My father, David Williams, came from the poverty of Ocho Rios, Jamaica. Downfall in life was women. He is a father of 6-7. But he works every day to make sure we were always taken care of. He had one son. Thought me what to do as well as what I shouldn't.
  - Dravon McKinnie left, and his father, Leo McKinnie, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0009)
    Sylvester, though not likely the idealized version of "black masculinity," Sylvester embodies what masculinity means to me. That means having the guts to walk, talk and stand in your own truth despite what others think. A man of color cannot develop a positive identity of himself unless those around him uphold and maintain his self-worth.
  - Hasani Sahlehe left, and his father, Vernon Morgan, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0010)
    I thought that I had to be big, strong, athletic, tough. I tried to be all of those things. I looked down on myself when I wasn't. I thought that others would too.
    When I was younger, I wanted to be Tupac or Bob Marley. That's where I got my philosophy. Two great men but now I see the world differently. I still love them both, but now I want to be Hasani. I've finally started to appreciate me for me.
    My experiences have made me who I am today. Unfortunately, those that are traumatic seem to have the most impact on my character. Not feeling accepted for who I was contributed to a desire in me to be accepted by all. I'm beginning to become more comfortable with who I am. I am so happy that I am able to become more and more like myself every day. It is still a struggle but one thing I know is that I wouldn't want to be anyone other than myself.
  - Ian Benboe, left, and his Father, Michael Nelson Benboe, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0011)
    They are still black men, which is something that can never be erased. Being black comes with direct and indirect ties to the birth of the civilization we reside in today. I used to deny my heritage, hoping to be more mixed and diverse. Now, I fully embrace my ethnicity.
  - Jonathan Magee left, and his father, Willace Demetris Magee, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0012)
    Everything in my life has helped me create a mold for the man I am and the man I want to be. Every trail brings new changes to my character. Every event evolves the nature of my soul. If I could change one thing in my life good or bad, I couldn't do it because every single thing has created who I am today.
    To me, the ideal figure that represents black male masculinity is my father. All his life he has worked hard and pushed himself for his family and is always teaching me new lessons on what it means to be a man.
    Do not worry about other people. No matter what you do someone in the world is going to hate you or what you have. So in the end, do not worry about it. Get yours, and have faith in yourself.
  - Kamall Browne left, and his father, Venzil Rawle Browne, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0013)
    Only speak ebonics (slang) All grew up in poverty All have baby mothers All have violent criminal backgrounds.
    I watch people's first assumption of me disappear the second I speak. Perceptions make people look at me like I'm dumb or illiterate. So many people are surprised to hear how intellectual I am after taking the time to get to know me.
    My father is the ideal figure for black male masculinity. He works his ass off just to provide for his family. He's been married for almost 25 years, had three kids, and never cheated on my mother. He's the most passionate person I know.
  - Lamarr Moore left, and his father, Larry Moore, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0014)
    I was told by my father at a young age that I was a black man, and my life would be harder because of it. I didn't understand that; I'm brown. Later I understood that our world operates in symbols and labels. Just as I am not literally black, white people are not white… Black is the label on our ethnic and cultural background, and I am glad to be in it.
    Role models played a very important role in my development. However, the majority of my role models growing up were women. My father's actions lead me to an understanding of the "provider". Whoever I have brought into my life, or whoever is special in my life should be taken care of.
  - Lindel Brown left, and his father, Medford Brown, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0015)
    In this photograph is a man of flaws like many of us, but who had great intentions. This man, who is my father, has been a great man to his children in teaching them the lessons that is necessary to live a decent life, more so to be an even better person. I am blessed and happy that I can say I have a father who loves and care for me and has been there when it mattered most.
  - Matt Cornwall left, and his father, David Alexander Cornwall, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0016)
    I don't truly believe there is an ideal figure of black male masculinity. Manliness is a series of qualities that we categorize into a certain group. No one can be 100% masculine though, it's impossible. If anything, the black male who doesn't chase such ideals would ironically be an ideal figure.
    Black masculinity is a phantom to me. I personally try to move towards it and I can never fully grasp it. However, my parents are black and I'm comfortable with the body I'm in right now, that's perfectly good enough for me.
  - Reeyon Rouse left, and his Father, Larry Rouse, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0017)
    There are perceptions of men of color. Being scary, rude, disrespectful, mad and always up to no good. It impacted me by making me try not to be any of the things. I have had experiences where I have judged by my skin. It has opened my eyes to what the world can be.
  - Jeremiah Thompson left, and his father, Joseph Thompson, Sr., 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0018)
    I have been afraid to express my true identity in the past because as a gay black man I could potentially be threatened, beat up, or killed. I've had friends who've been jumped and harassed because of their identity. Not to say I'm ashamed of who I am, but I have to protect myself. Being black is one thing, but being black & queer poses a different topic of discussion. This has shaped me into not hiding who I am, & understanding that representation is important because you never know who you are helping by being you. No one should live timid and afraid because of things they have no control over, such as skin color and sexual orientation. It's also shaped me to be fearless & fight for true unity amongst the black community. Not talking about something doesn't erase its existence.
  - Devin Hughes left, and his father, Philip Hughes, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0019)
    Setting a good example for the younger generation is vital. Being a minority in America isn't easy, having someone to look up to in a positive way can get you far. Having a strong male role model in my life molded me into the independent man I am today. I think being exposed to certain things at a young age shaped me early. I knew better when faced with them later in life because of my experience. Seeing negative things just makes me want more for myself.
  - Joshua Rashaad McFadden left, with his father, Craig McFadden, and grandfather, Robert McFadden, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11527-P-0020)
    Positive role models played a major role in my development as a black man. They provided inspiration, guidance, and knowledge. I learned so many things about my history from them. Things that I wouldn't have learned in the school systems. Growing-up with three brothers made it difficult to find my own identity. My father and grandfather always encouraged me to be unique. My mother did too. They also pushed me to get an education; they constantly told me and my brothers how it important it was. Black people will continue to face oppression in this country, but we must not let it stop us. We are powerful beyond measure. Please make an effort to be a positive role model in someone's life.